[Music]
the homework is due at the beginning of
class okay
and only a homework Tim which is
received at the beginning of class on
the following day after it was given out
will be accepted for credit you can
still give it later but it won't count
in your point total your point total
decides whether you get a nice
meditation cabin at Diamond Mountain in
the future and other such perks that I
can think of and there are no exceptions
okay I'm talking in I heard a rumor this
morning that one of the staff decided
they were too busy to do their
meditation and if I'm not too busy to
write it which takes about six hours
you're not too busy to fill it in which
takes about 20 minutes okay no
exceptions and no staff exceptions okay
you have to submit your homework if you
want to stay out there in John Brady's
cabin which is halfway to Mexico that's
okay by the way jump really have good
news for you this is a donation for ACIP
from our friends in Kazakhstan and
Azerbaijan which is very cool
and I think it's very cool it's both
Muslim countries and there's last time
we went there I think our 1500 people
came to the talk and I think it's really
beautiful so I'd like to congratulate
the Kazakhstan team and thank you very
much
[Applause]
yeah so homework time time okay yeah did
you have a question right okay we'll cut
you some song at the beginning of class
when you walk in the class you put your
homework in the box I guess right Tim or
Jackie
okay now quiz Tim made a really good
suggestion and I like it
he said geshe-la if you give them a quiz
before they see how they did on their
homework they will just repeat the same
mistakes they made on their homework so
we should hand out the homework master
which has long answers on it
correct long answers we should hand out
the math you know the homework master
early in the morning or something like
that and I'm afraid people just copy the
quiz questions or something so we have a
compromise today you will get the
homework master for yesterday's homework
and you study the correct answers and
then tomorrow the next day will give you
a quiz okay so that means unfortunately
you don't have a quiz today
and I'm very sad and I know you're also
son but today you will get the homework
master for homework number one and then
you will also get homework number two to
do right and then the quiz will be two
days later after you see the correct
answers okay deal
and I'm I'm gonna be serious okay I'm
not there are no exceptions and it's up
to you you know if you don't want to do
it
it's not a what he called first-grade
you know you have the right you are
adult you have the right to be stupid
and continue to be stupid and be stupid
for the rest of your life and you have
the right but I think it's stupid
so my dilemma Tommy don't say stupid
okay uninformed you can do that but I
suggest you work hard okay you worked so
hard to get here and you paid so much
money and work hard okay work hard
finish the homeworks and learn something
okay
take something home okay don't just
relax and let it go like level seven
lovely you know and learn something okay
and and you will be grateful later right
that's what your school teachers told
you okay I'd like to go through the life
story of Tony llama so you can
appreciate his life a little bit and
there's one homework question in there
is this working you guys like can you
tell there's one homework question in
there okay because his life was kind of
amazing alright so I'm just gonna go
quickly through his life it's in your
notebook I think and so I wrote it out
for you this is from an introduction to
a book that we finished in our
translator program at the city and it's
a commentary
okay this is from the introduction to
that translation it's a translation of
his commentary to the diamond cutter
Sutra which is the greatest commentary
ever written on the Diamond Sutra that
I'm aware of and I'd like to
congratulate all the translators I think
there's only one here today which is
Adam so thank you
[Applause]
his book is lodging and it's gonna be
finished in about eight years
okay so here's Tony Lamas life story
from that and I took it from there's a
biography written by his student who is
Adams author right sing on tushy and ten
years before he passed away in the final
year of his own life he wrote a personal
biography of him saw the biography and
usually Lamas won't tell you what their
personal experiences have been and he
didn't tell his student his own personal
experiences but in the last year of his
life I guess he figured what the heck
and he wrote down some of his personal
meditation experiences so I combined
them in this biography okay
so the but biography starts out with
boring facts about his life then it goes
to I think cool things he did that we
could kind of emulate things that we
could also do okay
personal things about him and then the
final part of this biography that I
wrote is his his private visions and
what happened to him during his a
lifetime of long lifetime at practice
okay so here we go here's the boring
part he was born in
which is northeast Tibet in 1675 at the
age of seven he started learning to read
and write which in those days was rare
and he seemed to learn very quickly at
the age of nine he received though we
call initial ordination baby ordination
you cannot become a monk until you're
twenty you're not allowed to make that
decision until you're twenty which is a
good system but you're allowed to try it
out from whenever you want to start so
you see baby monks running around the
monster but they're not real monks okay
so at nine he got his ordination from
the abbot of the Choni monastery so
Choni is his area like Kansas or Jalisco
or what's the state I don't know pick a
Chinese province I don't know anyway
such one okay whatever
okay so Tony is his province name okay
all right then there was a pattern in
Asia all over Asia Mongolians Chinese
Tibetans they would go to salsa the
capital of Tibet where the three great
monasteries are located and they would
study there at the age of twenty
twenty-one so at 21 he came to the
capital of Lhasa similar to what some
coppa had done three hundred years
before and this was a pattern I used to
live with a Mongol
monk who went to Fawcett to study
he took it took a camel across the Gobi
and and became a Samba gaerste in
endeavor monster I used to live with him
he was blind when I lived with him and
so this was very common even until then
the early 1900s okay and he studied at
sera monastery he wrote some of the
textbooks for our monastery sending me
okay
sanim a monastery he learned Adams texts
basic logic at a young age that was his
first debating topics then he went on to
abhidharma
and vanaya which is Stanley's topic and
Alison's topic there translating those
books and he stood for his Geshe
examinations at the age of 30 and he
debated before 20,000 monks and he was
awarded high cash a degree in 1706 he
received his full ordination so in those
days you might become a gadget before
you finish your full amongst us and them
no vision the the period when you are
still a baby monk not a full monk in
those days was much longer nowadays I
got mine together I got my division and
my full monk on the same day so nowadays
they sort of speed it up but in those
days you would take your first vows and
then they would watch you before for
many years and then they would give you
four of us okay
he entered to enter College which is one
of the two Tantra colleges in Tibet
and then he did what was kind of normal
in those times he went back home to his
own State Choni and he he he worked to
teach there and he built it's like if
you go back to Singapore and build SC I
am Singapore something like that so you
go back to your own country and you
build your your own monastery and you or
your own college and you start training
people okay so he went back and there
was a special position in those days
called washee-washee stanley and it's a
position it's like a government position
and the person in charge of that who's
sort of overseeing the province it's
like the educational minister of the
province was named non-soviet and he was
trying to build a gash in college at
Choni monastery and he asked Charlie
lama to do it so the quote Gor she was
the money honey okay he supplied the
money like somebody we know who built
our cafeteria and our new roads okay and
he was the money guy he gave the
financial support so Tony lama didn't
have to raise all the money himself and
he had time to teach and to write okay
and we see from his books that he wrote
even much later he's still talking about
this sponsor this big sponsor so I think
through his whole life he had this
relationship with an important sponsor
who helped pay for things in 1721 Tony
Lama resigned as the
of the Geshe college and he spent six or
seven years writing and that's probably
when he did his best work in 1727 the
girl she asked him to take the position
again and maybe there was a problem I
don't know and then in 1729 he was asked
to start a tantric college at his
monastery and he did okay for the study
of Tantra he resigned that position in
1737 and he spent the last 10 years of
his life really producing a lot of
beautiful books so many of the books we
have are from one of those two periods
in his life after he was kind of staying
at home and writing a lot okay
we found his writings his writings were
destroyed during the Cultural Revolution
and we couldn't find any copies and when
I was in Russia in the library in Russia
we found a set of his writings and so we
started to scan it and input it and we
were fortunate that we were John Brady's
project they spent 14 years in Russia in
the library and they were able to scan
the whole all of his works and we saved
them we had a staff member named Jason
Dunbar and you should thank him if you
ever meet him and he he put back
together Tony Lamas collected works and
then we put it up for free online so I
think we should give John a hand
[Applause]
[Music]
yeah about his style his writing style
is very almost Western so you know it's
not uncommon in Tibet for people to
write in a very fancy way that has no
information you know and it's kind of
frustrating and he was the opposite so
he just wrote exactly all the questions
come up in your mind he writes it and he
divides things carefully and he defines
things and he presents things extremely
well so that's why we're using his
commentary to wisdom because it's
unbelievable it's incredible you know
and what he does in the commentary is
why you are suffering in your homeworks
and I can't put everything he said in
the homework but it's unbelievable we
could spend 10 years easily on it but
he's a fantastic writer ok yeah he also
did a lot of deep retreats
ok so he wasn't just writing all the
time right Stanley he wasn't just
working all the time he also did deep
retreat so that his writing was was good
he studied Sanskrit and Mongolian and
sea and and when those people studied a
book
it wasn't the way we study a book he
would memorize the book so in the
monastery for example the first 12 years
of the gushie course is based on a
75-page text by my trail I'll be
somewhere Ankara
so we memorize it but we spent 12 years
with it and it's in your brain like when
you're washing dishes which is a very I
was the dishwasher for eight years your
your mind is reciting this text okay and
it's a very beautiful custom so I figure
you can do a homework
he was a fantastic memorizer he he went
to the winter debates the winner debates
is called Joong Geun Cho there was a
monastery called John and gunshow means
winter debates and it's a big deal yeah
you will pack up a backpack with one
month's food and you will hike like 2530
miles to this tiny monastery called junk
and all the normally nowadays it's the
50 best Geshe students from the six
major colleges plus touchy LUMO so seven
colleges and we will debate together for
a month and it's amazing because you get
to debate with the best guys from all
the colleges so it's like the
n-c-double-a it's like the Olympics of
debating and it's a very beautiful
custom because it means that the monks
who ten years or 20 years later will
become the head of those monasteries
they all know each other because they
debated each other at the winter dance
so they're already friends and it keeps
this lineage very tight so the the
management the administration the
highest caches of all the colleges they
know each other very well and it keeps
the lineage very cool and very sweet and
it's a big honor to go to the winter
debates so I invited myself
four times this is a record I think to
go four times it's a big honor and I got
fried there in different ways in the Sun
and from the other geishas but it's an
unbelievable experience it's like the
Olympics or something and there are
all-night sessions you to some of the
sessions you debate all night in there
it's really cool
okay he wrote two hundred and fifty
different works okay pretty amazing an
output and they are amazing he also his
books on Tantra his books on yoga his
books on the inner body are the best and
the best explanations of the inner body
the channels the chakras he's amazing
okay very thorough and we used his books
for the temple courts here which is 18
courses it's about 10,000 pages and I
don't think it's ever been done in the
world even in Tibet but we used his
books in law for the inner bodywork
here's Tony llama about his output I may
not have been a any great master but it
seems that in my past lives I made many
prayers to share this with them with
other people and that's why I was able
to write so much then his student Adams
book author said it more bluntly he said
Tony no majest worked harder than any
other Lama I ever saw okay it's cool all
right then I have a section about his
inner life okay which is kind of more
interesting and I'll just quote you some
things okay it seems like a lot of
people focus their private practice on
trying to see divine beings face-to-face
I've always thought it was more
important for me to focus on improving
my capacity to love others and feel
compassion for those in need and work
hard for a pure and peaceful world and
understand where reality itself is
coming from
[Music]
then his comment on meditation you know
there are deep states of meditation
concentration that often don't have any
particular spiritual content in
Scripture they are called they are
called the form realm meditations and
the formless realm meditations I see a
lot of people making efforts in these
myself I always thought it would be
better to try to master the Buddhist
practice of taking shelter where we
protect ourselves and others by
understanding the Buddha and emptiness
okay then he says the world is actually
a huge downward cycle painful events
triggered triggering reactions in us
that create the next painful event one
of the goals in my life was to try to
break this cycle
[Music]
about emptyness the main difference
between all the many different
historical schools of Buddhism is how
they view the concept of emptiness more
precisely what it is that emptiness is
empty of the idea of reality that we
have all the time and which is
completely mistaken how to fix this
problem acquaint yourself with what each
school believes is absent in emptiness
learn the gardener learn so coppa learn
chandrakirti the way to learn emptiness
is to sit and think it out carefully
there are a thousand different proofs of
emptiness to be found in the scripture
for goodness sake
learn them they will set you free then I
put in some you know going towards his I
don't know about his life okay first he
was no stranger to controversy or
politics okay and during his life he
lived during the time of the fifth Dalai
Lama who built the Potala Palace and the
fifth Dalai Lama had had a prime
minister who is called Daisy Sonya got
off and he was very very young he was in
his 30s and basically he was running the
country and the dilemma committed his
time to deep philosophical studies he
wrote many great books jumpa shalom one
of the first long rooms and he was very
tied up with his spiritual practice so
this other person ran the country
in 1682
the Fifth Element died and the minister
kept it secret for 13 years and he hired
an actor to pretend to be the dynamic
and so far so he could keep running the
country he was afraid the country fell
apart so he ran the country for another
13 years with a with a fake dial I'm an
actor okay and in those days you weren't
allowed to get near a famous like the
Emperor of China you weren't allowed
within about a hundred meters this was
just customary for his safety
okay so just before Tony Lama was
supposed to take his gadget degree like
the week before it was exposed that this
guy was fake and a Mongol princess came
and cut off the ministers head and stuck
it on a pole on on one of the bridges in
Gaza which caused a huge riot and there
were like twenty thousand monks came
into the capital and everything was like
crazy completely confused okay and then
he was supposed to take his final Joshy
but he chickened out and they they made
an announcement one of the head lamas
said let's have some super geeky debates
you know maybe everybody will calm down
and so let's have like super super
geisha two-degree debate let's create a
new game
- yep geishas and because all the monks
from all the monasteries are in town so
let's have a super debate you know and
he asked Tony Lamas Lama said you're
gonna you got a chance to be the gang of
our gaseous you know let's go me and go
for it
then he ran away
in left lhasa he left the capital he was
scared and then they say after two days
he got he felt guilty because he broke
his llamas command you know you're never
supposed to break your llamas request so
he felt bad and he was really scared but
he came back and he won okay like number
one guess you then it became famous and
after that everything was cool okay and
so he he he wasn't like some fairytale
llama he saw hard things he saw big
problems in his country he saw political
problems he saw he saw fighting he saw
murders he was a normal like us okay his
he was there he had a very strong work I
think and oftentimes he would lock
himself in his room for five or ten
years just to get away from fundraising
and administration and things like that
and there's a very famous incident where
his relatives came to bring him food and
he refused to open the door and he just
fasted he took responsibility okay when
he had to run the monastery he ran the
monster and he did a good job so he
wasn't afraid to build an institution
and raise the money and organize the
program of study he wasn't afraid of it
and he took responsibility and I think
we have to do the same he was also human
and there's a story see that he was
assigned content gherkin content gherkin
is Gashi Lottery's content Garrigan
means there are 12 colleges in Sarah
it's like Harvard or something and each
College has a house and each house has
about I don't know 30 to 275 baby monks
okay and someone has to babysit them you
know this is like the mom for the baby
monks their parents come and drop the
second or third son off at the monastery
and never come back and because they
can't feed them and then the monastery
is stuck with you know 200 kids and
nobody wants to watch the kids but and
so he was assigned constant gergan and
he ran away tell me until they chose
Herman yo this is very common nowadays
awesome when the abbot elections and my
monastery all the high gushes will leave
my Lama will go a thousand miles away he
has a retreat house when he hears
there's an election for gay Albert he
will run away he did many times okay he
was open to many different viewpoints
which is unusual in Tibet his father was
bum bum bum bum means knob Buddhist his
father was like local religion shaman
religion and he didn't follow Buddhism
so Tony lama learned but he learned this
other religion he understood it and he
appreciated it he appreciated the good
parts he was also trained by caucus
which are not some copper lineage and he
was known to respect them his father was
also practicing Nima which is another
tradition not some cop
tradition so Tony lama learned those and
he had some respect for them and he was
asked later in his life by some bumbles
to write the main ideas have done in a
book he said it's like that's a bond of
being asked to write abhidharma
when he was no longer following it and
he wrote one of the best books about the
bun religion unfortunately we haven't
found it so I'm not sure it still
survives but he was famous for being
open-minded okay he was very devoted to
his teachers there's a story of him
coming back from massara to his home
state and he goes through a village
where he meets one of his old Lamas and
but now he realizes what that lama
taught him was all mistaken now that
he's a Geisha he understands that what
he learned from that Lama was mistaken
but he wanted to help the Lama out of
respect and he was broke but he stayed
in the village for six months and he
worked at some dirty jobs like I don't
know ditch digging things like that so
that he could leave that Lama with some
money and take care of the Lama
so I think that shows he had a good
attitude about his teachers
[Music]
as a child as you say he saw it so these
are his compassion his mother got a
contagious disease and couldn't milk him
couldn't give him milk and he watched
his mother go through this disease at a
young age and I think it affected his
perception of suffering and I think it's
some other woman in the village milk
gave him milk and one of his first
visions in his life is that Tara is
coming to him and he's drinking Terris
milk from her breasts and I think it was
all tied together
then when he came back to his home state
he met his mother and it was a very
beautiful reunion but she died then she
died and something happened to him that
he he resigned that's why he resigned
the first time for seven years he went
into retreat for seven years because of
what happened to his mother and I think
that's some tone it's something about
him special that he had a deep love for
other people yeah he was famous for not
meeting famous people okay last thing
about his inner life okay and he he's
there's a tradition in Buddhism that you
don't talk about your inner life okay
there's a tradition that if you see
emptiness directly for example you don't
talk about it much and that's because
there's a very severe Karma to lying
about your spiritual life or
exaggerating about your spiritual life
okay so that's one of the four most
heavy Karma's there is okay and secondly
so he didn't share his inner life with
other people and then he said the second
reason I didn't share my in your life
was every time I share it it goes away
you know if I'm having some kind of
visions and I tell people about it I
don't have any visions for like six
months you know and then he decided
maybe I should just keep quiet about my
visions okay but
at the end of his life he wrote out some
of those visions and I think three of
them are very important for us and they
might be on your homework you never know
first one okay
the earliest dream I can remember came
to me when I was a very young boy and it
was repeated several times I am standing
on the ground outside my house and I'm
looking towards the east and far away in
the sky I can see somebody something
flying towards me and they kind of look
like Buddhas but I'm not sure you know
and they come over my head and they head
to the west okay and he says I used to
have this dream when I was a small child
many many times and any sense I still
don't know what it means this emphasis
on going to the west okay I think it's
cool
second dream I used to have another
dream I'm watching the East the sky to
the east and manjushri whose red golden
color is flying to the west again he's
on his way to the west manjushri is the
main Buddha for emptiness understanding
emptiness okay and he's going to the
West then when he gets over my head I
call up to him you know and I said
what's up man
I was thinking maybe he would stop for a
while and come down and I could do
prostration to manjushri so I was
thinking just to try to get him to stop
for a few minutes and then it comes down
and instead of standing there he melts
into Tony Lamas chest like that and then
he said in the dream I kept thinking to
myself oh now my Joshua's blessed me you
know I got my Jewish blessing okay
that's the second vision third dream
that he used to constantly have is
Nagarjuna okay
Arianna Gardner is flying through the
sky and he when he says nagarjuna's name
he says the one who saw emptiness
directly and wrote the greatest words on
this in this world on how to do it
yourself okay
that's how he describes in the God you
know then he said the god-honest body
was made of pure gold and it is shining
like the Sun and he's traveling to the
sky and he's headed to the west and I
don't know why and he also when he then
he pauses and he melts into me also okay
so personally Tony Lamas books are the
best explanation for us of emptiness and
bodhichitta and Bodhisattvas way of life
and Tantra they're the best books and I
think he had a vision of them coming to
the west okay
and that's all okay now let's start the
class okay
I thought you should know about King by
the way I went to I'm going to all the
bog of his anaconda that I can find
which are about five or six and I still
couldn't find any mention of when he saw
emptiness or you know how it happened
but I'm still I still have one more long
Banga fit to read okay
[Music]
don't King
okay so we're ready to start with them
all right we're ready to start the real
book and I'll give you a break in about
half an hour okay and I promise jig made
to be on time with the pp break all
right
and I thought I would read you the first
the first verse okay
it's probably the most famous uh
narottam uh Newt bottom a new chair damn
ash wash ash ash bottom and a carton
Anan item an R gamma a near Khammam yeah
potential Sampada prop on choke among
sebum - I am some Buddhist nun bun David
Adam Burnham
okay roughly in English okay I haven't
translated I bow down to the highest of
all teachers to the fully enlightened
Buddha who teaches piece which is the
piece in which we no longer see things
that aren't there
okay I bow down to this teacher who
taught that all things occur
independence okay who taught that
nothing stops who taught that nothing
starts who taught that nothing is ever
cut off who taught that nothing lasts
forever there's nothing which doesn't
change who taught that nothing comes who
taught that nothing goes who taught that
there is that there are no separate
things and who taught that know things
are one okay this is the first verse
very famous there are eight things that
he denies okay there are eight things in
the verse which he says do not exist
okay and that's why we call this course
aid Invisibles okay so if you wonder
where the name came from its from the
first verse of the most famous
explanation of emptiness ever
okay and we're gonna talk about that
first purse okay especially as it
relates to your homework okay so
traditionally when you start writing a
scripture a holy book spiritual book
you're supposed to do by tradition two
things at the beginning okay number one
you're supposed to honor the lineage and
your teacher okay so at the beginning of
every Buddhist book you will see
prostration - holy being some teachers
or - teacher of the tradition so this
first verse is bowing down to Lord
Buddha and thanking the Buddha for
teaching dependence okay which is
there's two ways to teach dependence one
is you just teach the twelve links you
know why you commit come on Karma why
you misunderstand things but there's a
deeper way to teach the wheel of life
where you teach emptiness at the same
time okay so that's the cool thing that
is contained in the first verse he has
to bow down to somebody that's the rule
okay so he bowed down to Buddha but he
says I'm not just dying down to you cuz
you're Buddha I'm bowing down to you
because Utah dependence like in the lion
stands right and then you went deeper
and you taught the deep version of
dependence which as you mentioned
emptiness eight kinds of emptiness okay
they aid Invisibles so you are so cool
you are the greatest of all teachers
okay because you show us the way to
final peace okay final peace so that's
the verse right
so in when he come dear cheeky Shou and
he said with one bullet he kills two
deers which is a bad image when you call
it English I'll kill two birds with one
stone they're both bad images but you
get the idea he bows down to the Buddha
okay
and secondly he covers good soaked
Russia say good soak sushi sushi very
very very famous okay at the beginning
of a Buddhist book you must indicate
that this book has four qualities okay
it's a seal of approval by Buddhism that
your book is a good book okay if the
book has these four qualities it's a
Buddhist book and you can spend your
time on it and you can expose your
precious mental territory to this book
and you will have good results okay so
it's even in the bodhisattva vows right
we can't waste time on videos on YouTube
are worthless books newspapers about
what stupid thing did trump do today
okay now why do you want to smell a fart
five times six times you know just
forget it it's not worth your time you
don't have time okay if you work very
hard you might get enlightened and not
dying but if you don't you will die and
you'll be back you know people will be
sneaking food to you at Diamond Mountain
you'll be an animal at Diamond Mountain
you see you you have those two choices
you
time or or be a bug at Diamond Mountain
it's up to you it's cheaper to be a bug
at time mine but I mean that's your
choice okay we don't have time to waste
on silly things okay and the Internet is
95% silly things okay there are some
cool things on the Internet
there are some beautiful things on the
Internet you can use it but most of us
just crap and so there's a tradition in
Buddhism that the author will indicate
in the opening lines that this book is
worth your time this book is worth your
precious time and the Guardian is
showing off because in one verse in the
first verse he squeezes in the
frustration and he squeezes in the four
qualities of a good book that you can
spend your time on okay so what are the
four just in case it's on your homework
okay
and by the way 12 centuries later
jetsam coppa writes a whole book called
a song to the buddha for teaching the
emptiness version of the Wheel of Life
okay that he stole it directly from he
got the idea from the gardener he what
he called he ran with the idea and he
wrote a whole book it's one of his most
famous books it's a poetry and it's
extremely beautiful extremely powerful
okay we translated it well but we have
it somewhere maybe you can find it
jing-mei yeah
yeah so maybe you can make a print
version for everybody okay it's Jets
okapis plagiarism based on the first
verse of Nagarjuna okay
and it's he took it and he went with it
you know okay all right
four qualities of a Buddhist book number
one it must have important topic
important subject okay must have all
right
and you must indicate that to the reader
at the beginning of the book the topic
which is important is dependence okay
you can say Wheel of Life you can say
past life movie during lions dance okay
that's dependence but teach it with
emptiness teach it together think about
how your Lama came to you think about
how your Lama didn't come to you okay we
have both of them at level 9 of the
lions dance we have dependence we just
sing what past life thing caused your
teacher okay and we have emptiness which
is where you think about how your
teacher didn't come to you by accident
okay we have both in the lions dance
okay so this book advertisement cover we
are teaching dependence but with eight
kinds of emptiness okay eight Invisibles
okay we have not just one not just two
not just before we can eight kinds of
emptiness in this book
you guys gotta buy it okay Wow with your
mental time okay all right okay quality
number two there should be an immediate
goal of this book you know within a few
hours of reading this book there should
be some short-term goal immediate goal
okay and that goal which is called GABA
in Tibetan is if you read this book you
will understand dependence with
emptiness
okay the emptiness version of dependence
you will understand okay that's the
second advertisement for this book okay
number one it has important subject
matter what dependence seeds right with
emptiness then what's the second good
thing about this book if you read it you
will understand
that dependence and those emptinesses
does eight and you will understand okay
got it all right quality number three of
a good book
there should be an ultimate goal okay
there should be an ultimate gone and
that's why the text mentions well that's
why the verse mentions peace okay peace
that's the gun okay there's two kinds of
peace here okay one is nirvana well you
don't have any more anger you don't have
any more jealousy you don't have any any
more desire okay but it's also referring
to a higher peace which occurs during
the direct perception of emptiness okay
during the direct perception of
emptiness you you are in a kind of peace
where you no longer see anything coming
from its own side okay got it and that's
that's also peace if you read this book
if you understand dependence and the
eight kinds of emptiness you can reach
peace these two kinds of peace you can
see emptiness directly and that will
lead you to Nirvana and Buddhahood okay
got it alright quality number four of a
good book is there's a connection
between the other three okay if you read
the words you will understand the ideas
and they will take you to enlightenment
and the direct perception of emptiness
quality to depends on quality one
quality three depends on quality too
okay if you read the book you will see
you will understand dependence on
emptiness if you understand it
intellectually then you will reach the
ultimate goal of seeing it directly okay
got it
so there's a connection between 1 & 2 &
1 & 3 & 2 & 3
got it those are the very very famous
okay if you go to sera monastery and you
say I studied anything
the first question a monk will ask you
so what's a good soldier she you know
what's the cuz they they think if you if
you were in the first class you heard
those four and I failed that test one
day so I will never forget he's like
give me the good soldier huh I'm just
trying to save you some embarrassment
okay this they they think any idiot who
studied any Buddhist book should learn
those four on the first day and if you
say you're a Buddhist and you say you
studied with a Geisha and you don't know
those four it's like you fail before you
start understand okay what is dependence
and I'm following Tony Lama okay I'm not
most of these are not my own ideas I'm
just stealing stuff from his commentary
okay which I don't have time to
translate and I could translate it in in
three weeks if I had any time but you
might be in Tony Lama says let's look at
what how the gardener defines dependence
okay
later in the book okay which is in the
eighth chapter okay
in the eighth chapter somebody asked the
gardener can you define dependence in
like one sentence okay what is
dependence okay and here's the sentence
the people who do things okay the people
who do things depend on what they do and
what they do depends on them okay ready
here we go again when you do something
you depend on what you do
and what you do depends on you it's
mutual dependence mutual dependence one
of those is easy one of those is hard
okay you want me to do the easy one or
the hard one let's do the easy one
you're right
let me try to fundraise for an endowment
for our college and people are helping
and thank you the people who are helping
thank you okay it's not all on me people
are taking responsibility John's taking
on responsibility and so we are working
and and Jenny's team is awesome and
they've collected like a zillion dollars
from Singapore anyway yeah
but because of Jenny's work there will
be an endowment okay so that's the doer
the doer is Ginny the thing she does is
the endowment okay so which comes first
yeah first there has to be Jenny to
fundraise then there will be this
endowment with the resolve of the
Singapore people's hard work okay they
work hard and because of their hard work
there's a result so that's obvious
there's a dependent relationship if
there's no Jenny there's no endowment
okay if there's no Jenny there's no
endowment but the gardener says if
there's no endowment
there's no sponsor
[Music]
if there's no endowment there's no
sponsor okay
if they succeed if the Singapore people
succeed and we have the endowment right
then we can say they paid for it we can
say they are responsible we can say they
are the cool people okay you don't get
to be cool people until after the
endowment you see you're raising money
you're not cool people yet you're just
raising money if you succeed then
everybody call you cool people so that
endowment cause you mutual dependence
okay darling usually the second kind of
dependence is called name dependence
named dependence we cannot call Jenny
successful sponsor until the indominus
finished okay did she cause the
endowment yeah but did the endowment
cause her to be called what she is
called dependent both ways
Gani okay cannon cool that's in the
Gardiners definition of dependence in
the eighth chapter okay got it that's
that's chill right in surfing you call
it that's really sick man that's really
sick sick meets fantastic in surfing
that was a sick wave you got man yeah I
know I was really sick it's really sick
definition of dependence
okay Jenny caused the endowment and the
endowment cost Jenny got it even though
I came later his sentence you really
want that the agents those who do things
depend on the action that they take
while the action they take depends in
turn upon the agents he puts the easy
part second he puts this easy part
second actions depend on agents right
but agents also depend on actions okay
only after you have completed check this
out
only after a seed has created a tree can
that seed be called
a cause you see you don't deserve the
name until you give your baby then we
call your mom you saying you can't call
a seed a cause until the result comes
out okay after the tree is there
somebody say who had that come from you
say the scene is the cause you don't get
to be called a cause until there's a
result cool
that's real dependence and if you read
pub uncas commentary and the three
principal paths anybody remember for
$100
how does he describe this principle no
more $2,000 so I can go too hard it took
me like six weeks to pay that 100 bucks
I was laughing all right I don't like it
okay they call it the tripod some pop
uncle calls it the tripod tripod means
when you're cooking over a fire on a
tibetan picnic you have to have three
sticks that support each other the three
sticks support each other if you take
away one stick that other two fall down
okay it means Jenny depends on the sari
the endowment depends on Jenny
but Jenny also depends on the endowment
they are they are leaning on each other
like like like these two things you see
and if you pull out one the other one
will fall down okay that's how a bunker
now I know that was a very advanced
reading in a CI number one you all just
failed the ACI of course it's 1024 what
are the three ways to become the most
popular professor at the Sedona College
number one know your stuff
backwards and foreigns number two no the
students names
number three
and let them always end the class early
okay go peepee you have five minutes
early we have something else no I lied
is it ready okay we might as well not
waste our precious mind space until they
come back I'll give you the next
homework question for free in wisdom we
are examining many different proofs why
things are empty many different proofs
this is wisdom this is the book what is
the attitude of a bodhisattva about many
proofs of emptiness and what is the
attitude about many proofs of emptiness
of a person who's not a bodhisattva and
why is the difference why different
what's the difference okay you want the
answer for free okay you have to give me
some cake okay birthday cake I can smell
it coming
oh okay quick body stuff is like many
proofs of emptiness they say a thousand
there were a thousand why number one
they want to make sure that got it
correct they want one thousand proof of
emptiness okay number two what they want
a big toolbox Bodhisattva wants a big
toolbox okay because your students some
of them will understand proof number one
some of them will understand proof
number two some of them won't understand
even after thousandth so Bodhisattva
wants a big box of proofs okay this is
the difference other people
lower lower Hinayana right they're like
teach me one proof is enough Gettler I
don't want more I will get confused okay
so that's a big difference between a
bodhisattva a person who wants to save
the world and a person who's not
interested in saving the world
the person who saves the world they want
more proofs of emptiness
give me more proof give me another proof
okay then other people are like one
thing knife - now go meditate on it okay
okay we're gonna do a small scare a
small play which comes from DCI and it
explains the whole wisdom in five
minutes and I think it's very powerful
so you over here it's more comfortable
for me so just have fun and this little
play includes all of dependents and all
of emptiness okay and I think the ain't
Invisibles are in there also okay so
this way you can understand in an easy
way and then we'll talk about the
technical
sanskrit words and things like that but
this is the meaning of the whole thing
and the whole point of wisdom is to use
it in your life right the whole point of
this week is to use it in your real life
so this is the way we teach it to people
like in kazakhstan they will never be
buddhist we don't expect them to be
buddhist we didn't something they can
use in their life right okay here we go
all right here we go so I'm a typical
mother in I don't know Singapore or
Moscow or whatever it is and nowadays
I'm a working mother right which means
my husband gets to relax at home and I
make all the money and I have to do the
traditional jobs of a woman which is
take care of the kids and cook the food
so it's a Wednesday and I'm leaving work
and my boss says don't forget tomorrow
you got to come one hour early because
we are an international company and we
have a conference call with New York
from Shanghai and you know we decide to
do it early in the morning which is late
in New York and you have to be here an
hour early you understand and the bosses
eyebrow goes up which means tired
if you don't okay you're fired if you
don't come so you know you're like you
see the eyebrows go you're like okay I
understand
I know what you're saying I know what
you're telling me you know I really do
have to come an hour early tomorrow it's
not an option okay then you go and tell
your kids okay you guys going to you
guys we go you guys be my kids okay you
guys be my kids okay
you're my two kids all right then I come
home and I go to my kid's room and I
said kids you know usually mommy comes
at eight o'clock to take you to school
but tomorrow Mommy has a special job in
money has to be leave at seven o'clock
and mommy just asking you please be
ready for school have you
we're finished be all dressed for school
don't forget to tie your shoes
everything yourself okay can you guys do
that tomorrow because I'll tell you
mommy's gonna get fired if you guys
can't do that okay you agree okay
yeah two kids agree okay then a mommy's
like God okay she comes in the room the
next morning one hour early seven
o'clock and the kids are fighting with
each other they are kind they are still
in pajamas the shoes are missing and the
homework is also missing and mommy's
like I told you I gotta be there an hour
early you know this is you can't do this
to mommy mommy's gonna get fun you are
the stupidest kids in where you guys
from what's your city home city jb the
other JP oh they're from malaysia okay
oh you are more stupid kids in Johor
Bahru
you know then side ah ah then they start
to cry then question who heard mommy say
you are the most stupid kids in Johor
Bahru they heard that's why they cry
anybody else
yeah mommy also heard okay you are the
most stupid kids in Jobar oh okay then
mommy hurting then those words go into
mommy's ear and they make an impression
on mommy's mind okay
mind is like clay and it leaves an
impression on mommy's mind then when you
teach it go like this and you same when
you teach the four steps go like this
and say after few hours four hours that
impression becomes a state in mommy's
mind okay then mommy has a bad seat in
mommy's mind okay then next week Monday
mommy is coming home she pick up the
kids from school they are being good
today thank you and we buy groceries and
we come home
and I'm thinking you know why did I get
married you know if the husband doesn't
work anymore
what's a functional husband then can
think well one good thing my husband
always gives me a good hug when I come
home
the one thing my husband can do besides
TV he can he can give me a good hug you
know and it's worth it you know a good
hug it's okay my life is okay I get home
I'm tired I take the kids I have to make
the money I have to buy the groceries I
have to cook the food but at least when
I come home my husband gives me those
great hugs she opens the door to the
kitchen she says hello honey
so phantom means rice bucket head which
means your idiot okay so try to learn a
bad word in every language it's good
okay say him phantom phantom okay you
are right bucket head pin eyes I'm like
what I didn't do anything I just don't
put the door I didn't say anything to
him I just hope at the door he starts
yelling at me I don't know what's wrong
with my relationship he doesn't let me
anymore he used to give me hug now he
called me stupid the minute openeth Ryan
do anything is it true she didn't do
anything not true
what did she do she yelled at the kids
not swing and she put a seat in her mind
then the moment she opened the door
that's it open and she the husband come
out of the seat you see yelling husband
come out of the seat okay so now next
question how can she prove she's stupid
how can she prove she's fun Tom yeah
you're back say it back I'm not stupid
you're stupid okay all right there what
will happen next week kids will be bad
okay
why cuz she called stupid sorry she
called the husband stupid
okay so what happened here makes need
over there see it open here makes it
over here see it open over there over
here over here over here over here
what's that called in Buddhism samsara
samsara okay Wheel of Life
okay that's a perfect answer so don't
think samsara is a it has to be three
lifetimes or something like that you
make some cyrus every five minutes every
five minutes you are making nuisance are
in your life and and also in Stanley's
text is called catching Me Tender
dependent origination in an instant in
five minutes
five-minute dependent origination you
can do it okay
you are creating it okay how to break it
well you have to understand the two
husbands so when you teach it you have
to be funny right and you have to say
maybe you are wondering why Geshe
Michael has two husbands okay why are
there two husbands in the kitchen well
actually this one is called his special
name is I didn't do anything husband
okay all right her name his name is I
can't do anything husband okay
this husband didn't come from me I don't
know why he's the owner he called me
stupid fun tone I don't know where he'll
get this one called I didn't do anything
husband this one come from me okay this
husband comes from me dependent
origination husband okay he came because
I yelled at the kids last week okay this
one came because I yelled at the kids
last week now question one of those
husband really exists and one of those
husband cannot exist which is which
which is shopping
yeah cannot exist there's no such thing
they don't exist
impossible husband who didn't come from
me is impossible how about this husband
possible or not yeah very possible
super possible okay this one comes from
me because I yelled at the kids last
week okay now deeper question and this
is very very important for nirvana
Nirvana means you stop your anger
forever right Nirvana means you can stop
your anger forever so when I get upset
when I come in the kitchen he calls me
funtom I am upset at one of them which
one shall ping why why can't I be upset
why I'm not upset is standing why I
understand where I come from okay who
like get upset
she'll get upset at me right okay when I
get upset when I get angry it's only
possible if you don't see emptiness okay
it's impossible to get angry if you see
emptiness okay because you realize she
don't exist she never existed
okay impossible this one this one is
coaching this one is empty this one how
did Buddha say it for $50.00 how did
Buddha said okay cancel the bed
never won she was never in the kitchen
number two she's not in the kitchen now
number three she will never be in the
kitchen in the future she is totally
impossible cannot be she's not there if
you think she's there
you are having illusion she's Maya
that's illusion okay
there is no shopping there is no husband
there okay how many husbands in the
kitchen just one really only one okay
and when you get upset when you get
upset you're angry at this one okay why
why cannot get upset at this one this is
when you understand oh I'm this one
okay watch and come in
okay okay go to the toilet open the door
look in the mirror you're so stupid
okay got it that one's correct that
one's okay alright understand so
everything is here
there's where's the Kong Ching where's
emptiness yeah she was never here in the
kitchen
where's dependent origination yeah
where's the truth of the source of
suffering nice over there where's the
truth of suffering for your fat dog when
the kids cry right where's the truth of
the end of suffering in the toilet
where's the truth of the path to the end
of suffering walking to the toilet okay
stay quiet now for all the women in the
room last thing when you teach it last
thing
look privately between the women and me
it's true all husbands are stupid okay
we know we already agree but don't say
it don't make bad seat okay it's true
but never say okay we all know we don't
have to say okay just stay quiet okay
got it does that mean if your husband
hurts you you should say oh that's okay
no you should go tell somebody you
should get some help okay and you don't
let people hurt you that's not what I'm
saying but if you want to stop it in the
future
stop yelling at your kids okay got it
all right now we can talk about
nagarjuna Thank You Stanley
[Applause]
okay
Oh No okay easy homework question number
five how many chapters does wisdom have
the answer is 27 there are 27 chapters
they are very short some of them are
half a page okay 27 short and the
gardener bomb bombs
okay in the garden of bombs okay 27 each
one is called Patricia Patricia means
let's examine something
let's check something does it come from
its own side or not what was the first
one husband okay you can say part Berta
it's called Berta wife is called Berta
in sanskrit birthday party sure let's
look into husbands and wives okay I
don't know the word for husband but
let's check so partition each chapter is
called examination about some question
okay what who where did the husband come
from okay so each chapter is called
partition para means around like
periscope perimeter and it sha means to
see or to check in to and the German
word for I is a ye algún and the English
word ocular comes from not and it means
to look into something action action to
look into something buttocks are let's
look into 27 different things in the
world let's look into 27 different
subjects and I'm going to teach you the
27 tomorrow tomorrow you're hooked you
have to get a lot of sleep tonight
because tomorrow is a rough day homework
wise is super update tomorrow okay
you're going to learn the 27 chapters
and what they what they talk about okay
like there are some sexy ones like who
made the connection between karma and
its results
like that they're all like cool all
right
I'm going to give you the names of the
first three chapters just because it's
on your homework it's just for example
okay the first chapter is called an
examination of conditions
I put factors yesterday but he is the
different word for factors later in a
later chapter sorry about that
so causes and conditions right
conditions conditions means water
fertilizer sunlight cause means see
trees seed okay conditions means
sometimes in sanskrit condition can mean
any cause all the causes okay so the
very first chapter we're going to check
what makes a cause a cause okay what
makes it who made causes okay that's the
first chapter ii chapter is it possible
to come and is it possible to go okay
he actually calls it going and coming
okay is it how does that work that
something goes and comes okay how does
that work how is that possible
alright third chapter an examination of
the powers of sense your eyes your ears
your nose your tongue okay that's just
the first three so I'm gonna be merciful
today you just need to know three on
your homework and tomorrow that's
another story okay so if you're gonna
run away run away tonight okay then we
are examining does this thing come from
me or not does this husband come from me
or not and we are exam that's the main
examination who made the connection
between karma and the results of karma
okay things like that deep questions
okay who made emptiness
all right all right I'm going to give
you the aid Invisibles in the first
verse of wisdom they are a single word
they are a single word okay I'm going to
give you the eighth in the order of the
verse okay and I'll just give you one
word then Tony lama explains the one
word briefly okay so I'm going to tell
you the aid Invisibles each one has a
name it's just a single word and Tony
lama puts in two or three words to
clarify okay because some of them look
similar okay
all right first one things that could
stop things that could stop moment by
moment and here's the punchline okay on
their own on their own without yelling
at the kids understand I didn't is that
I didn't do anything stopping okay this
my girlfriend told me she found another
man my relationship just stopped okay
then I get breathing right no impossible
that's the first invisible okay
my girlfriend's stopped our relationship
I didn't do anything I didn't say
anything I didn't do anything she
stopped she stopped the relationship
okay then on its own it stopped it's not
my fault
I didn't do anything you know I didn't
mess around I didn't do anything
she just stopped okay true impossible
okay we can call it in visible invisible
you cannot see that kind of stopping
okay
who's the invisible husband in our
example elephant invisible okay I don't
have two husbands in my kitchen don't
think I'm weird guy weird weird wife I
don't have two husbands in my kitchen
one is invisible cannot exist okay
that's what invisible means all right
when we say aid invisible that's the
husband in the kitchen who didn't come
from me
it's invisible there's no such thing
there's no such thing but which one you
get angrier invisible huh okay when you
have a world war and 100 million people
die who's the enemy we're the enemy come
from another country
no they come from you okay got it there
I'm visible the enemy who come from an
other country is invisible there's no
enemy who came from another country when
you have a world war and you kill a
hundred million people you are fighting
nothing literally nothing there is no
enemy came from another country doesn't
exist cannot exist got it that's the
problem with not understanding this book
you can have a world war you can kill a
hundred million people if you don't
understand this book you see you cannot
have a world war if you understand this
book not possible okay impossible you
can't get us angry at a husband who's
not there it's not possible okay so but
we feel he's there right we feel he's
there and it takes a lot of proofs for
emptiness to stop that feeling it takes
many many proofs it's not enough to talk
about the husband in the kitchen one
time you have to hear it over and over
and over again and we have to talk about
pans and we have to talk other things
okay over and over because to defeat a
mistake that you have made for a billion
years is not easy okay one logic is not
enough okay
you have been making this mistake for a
billion years
okay we just had 5 minutes 5 minutes
cannot stand against 1 billion years
okay all right the mind has been going
for a billion years you can't fight that
in five minutes but but five minutes of
the kitchen story I don't know it's
worth about 100 lifetimes okay you just
cut a hundred lifetimes and off of your
misunderstanding okay
because truth is stronger than lie okay
that's the final gadget question every
gadget has to enter the truth will
succeed truth always stronger okay
the kitchen is stronger than the yelling
kids all right all right okay
so Tony llama says the stopping which
the Guardian I mentioned first is
specifically talking about stopping
moment by moment okay because there's
another stopping in the list there's
another stopping in the list okay so
don't get confused this one is the one
you know that husband coming from you 65
seats per second right open-close
open-close open-close open-close okay
that kind of stopping doesn't come from
itself it comes from the Seas okay cool
second one nothing can start from its
own side from not being there before
okay you open the door to the kitchen
and they're yelling what start the
yelling starts right husband mouth open
just the opening mouth mom this also not
coming from its own side so stopping
doesn't come from its own side and
starting doesn't come from its own side
okay that's the second invisible okay
he start yelling at me I don't know why
if you understood emptiness you wouldn't
see any yelling coming from your husband
okay got it second invisible second in
December
got it all right third one this is a
another kind of stopping but it's a
favor of stopping okay
it means cut off okay the thing is going
for a month your relationships going for
a month your relationship is going for a
year your relationship is going for 25
years and then cut cut off okay that's
the third one okay so it's a little bit
different from the first one first one
is stopping moment by moment second one
is stopping after six years relationship
ten year relationship then suddenly got
cut off
okay that also doesn't come from itself
okay it's invisible should be invisible
okay number four some things never
change
in that sense they don't end moment to
moment like one empty space okay there's
space this bottle is in space if I take
the bottle out of the space what happens
to the space it's still there if I blow
up the whole world
it will stay that space will stay here
location okay it's occupied ocupado or
no ocupado in America finally they stock
up atom but it stays there it always
stays there okay no one can change it it
never changes okay that also is
invisible if you think it's coming from
the outside it's not the space in which
things live the universe was created by
your mind okay the space that planets
and stars and people walk through was
created by you okay all right
number five
nothing can come towards you on its own
okay from its own side and we'll talk
more about it but when you walk when
when someone walks up to me if I'm
sitting here and someone walks up to me
there's no person walking up to me it's
a small picture bigger picture bigger
picture
big big big picture big big big picture
they asked me for some appointment to
talk about their stuff I say no then the
picture gets smaller smaller we got we
designed a new DCI t-shirt but I didn't
have the courage to make it it says a
shut up and do the four steps anyway so
yeah nobody comes towards you it's just
small picture big picture big picture
from your seat then when they walk away
which is number six okay five has come
towards you six is go away okay then the
picture gets smaller and smaller and
smaller and smaller coming from you okay
nobody's coming nobody's going okay all
right you but you did not come in the
kitchen and you did not leave the
kitchen okay the kitchen got bigger and
bigger bigger the kitchen door got
bigger bigger bigger and then the
kitchen door got smallest - mark and you
came and you left okay that's all mm-hmm
geshe-la
you're getting weird you know it start
to sound like I'm very drunk or
something you know so why why do I need
to know that you know why do I have to
stop every time I walks your door and
think Oh door getting bigger bigger
bigger door getting smart smart smart
you know
then I'm enlightened person you know
that's weird no the point is of course
that we would all like to live with a
perfect husband or perfect why of course
this is a half of 50% of human life is
your relationships so if they're not
coming from you you can't change them
you can't fix them if they are coming
from you well then you can design a
better husband here's the cool part
without talking to them ok you don't
need to talk to them to change them you
don't have to say don't call me fun tone
you know maybe I'm a gold bucket head
but not a right head again and
when you talk to your husband maybe it
works maybe it doesn't work you know
that it's not a methane it's not a path
and can change your seeds with your kids
paint your husband will change he has to
change
dependent origination he's dependent
origination
ok got it if the door is getting bigger
bigger bigger smart smart smart
that's good news why you can fix your
husband without talking to him it's it's
a it's an art at a DCI talk we teach
people how to get their husband to wash
the dishes and you don't know how many
success stories we have you know even
some husbands are cooking now which is
almost impossible okay last one seven
and eight seven and eight is this bottle
the same as this Cup know who made it
that way
I did I did okay is the cup the same as
the cup yeah it is is one thing okay
it's one thing kill kill kill you become
a teacher this is an atom's text
everything exists it is
itself okay definition what are the
definition of existence yeah is one
thing possible that's number eight yes
oh yeah of course but not from itself
one things one things are possible this
is number eight one things are possible
but they are coming from you two things
are also possible but they're also
coming from you that's number seven okay
more than one thing got it I'm trying to
this way I did really good for three
weeks I had a million dollar bet with
somebody and I won and but I wanted like
two or three more pounds it just won't
happen
nope I didn't eat for like a week it
just won't happen you see so one is not
one and two is not to understand coming
from somewhere else it's not coming from
food it's some kind of evil see the last
two pounds sing kind of people's scene
you understand is it one or is it many
how much I lost the last week it's not
many I'm sorry
it's one Gunung who made things more
than one I did who made them just one
like the last pound I have to lose I did
okay that one is permanent and
unchanging just kidding okay excuse me
sorry oh six was could go go away on its
own yeah five is towards six is away
okay
why are they invisible you don't need me
to tell you it's on your homework but in
general the second husband shopping
cannot exist so she's invisible that's
why we say invisible ok that's why we
see invisible but there's a second
reason why it's invisible ok there are
many things which cannot be seen by a
person who is seeing emptiness directly
while you're watching emptiness directly
there are many other things you cannot
see ok like donuts but also you cannot
see shopping while while you are seeing
Angeles directly
you cannot see the husband what do we
call the husband which one I can't do
anything husband you gotta say it with
possess we need Ayrton I don't do
anything husband ok
Wow and first of all they don't exist so
they're invisible but secondly if you
are seeing emptiness directly you
actually cannot see them impossible ok
so two meanings of invisible for your
homework ok last thing on this question
I might go a little bit over Tim why did
I enter garden I choose these aids
specifically each one relates to your
real life ok each one of these 8 relates
to your real life ok number one is the
husband ever going to stop yelling
moment to moment is he ever going to
stop well that depends on your seats ok
did he ever start I mean don't you want
to know why your husband started too
young when you didn't do anything don't
you want to know why do you want don't
you want another real reason why people
start to hurt you ok
why you got first moment of car accident
don't you want to know why they started
okay that's the second one third one how
can I stop this problem in my life you
know my husband how can I cut it off
okay number four is it unchanging is it
or I want unchanging
happiness I want happiness forever okay
number five there are certain people I
don't want to number five
come to me I like to stay away number
six
there's some people I don't want them to
go I don't want them to go okay that's
number six number seven I don't know you
would like to lose multiple pumps and
not single pound you seen I mean you
think of your own example anyway
neck job in the garden I chose this in
because everything in your life revolves
around these aim everything involves
coming going starting stopping being on
being many everything is the same
okay everything is wrapped up in these
name your whole life is eight parts okay
everything in your life has eight points
okay what's the aid in his first birth
things are never one by themself
number seven things are never many by
them son okay later
the Saint became very very famous proofs
of emptiness there are many proofs of
emptiness here we'll talk about it okay
alright question number seven what has
the idea of peace got to do with these
eight Invisibles let's talk about peace
in the kitchen what's it got to do with
invisible husband
how can invisible husband help you to
have peace in the kitchen
if you realize he was never there
then you're gonna calm down okay if you
realize oh the husband who's yelling at
me because he decided to yell at me
doesn't exist okay he doesn't he's not
yelling at me because he decided to you
that's not who's making him yell
who's making him young you the husband
who decided to yell at you is never
there doesn't exist cannot exist never
existed in the past
impossible invisible okay that husband
is it's not there if you understand that
in the moment in the kitchen you will
get some peace you will get some peace
does it hurt to have husband yell at you
yes does it hurt to have husband that
you created yell are you yes but do you
feel better about being in the kitchen
yeah
because you know how to stop it for the
future okay you know how to stop it's
the same in your meditation my knees are
hurting guess not okay plant a seed you
know massage somebody else's knees
during meditation okay
not the cute boy in the class okay but
massage someone's knee then maybe
tomorrow it won't hurt okay come from
you the pain in your knee was created
because you hurt somebody
okay so you can get some peace now
immediately some peace why this is under
my control I can change it I have power
I have power that's peace right then
when you change it you get more peace
okay ultimate peace there's two kinds of
peace here and I want to see two kinds
of peace in your answer okay well the
first kind of peace has two parts okay
number one you feel better in the
kitchen you don't keep the fight going
okay and number two if you keep refusing
to answer
the husband will stop yelling in time
okay that's the first general kind of
piece okay second if you keep that up in
your life day after day after day with
everything bad you'll reach nirvana okay
and no one will ever yell at you a
Buddhahood okay you are surrounded by
sweet buddy stop bus okay okay that's
final piece okay final piece so in this
first verse the guardian of promises you
two kinds of piece number one more peace
in the kitchen
number two more peace forever don't have
to die that's also caused by seeds okay
aging caused by seeds you can stop it
all right last question no here's a very
cool thing and you only get this thing
from Tony Leung okay so it helps to come
from the best monastery in Tibet said of
me Tony Lama asks a question why didn't
the gardener start with stopping and he
didn't start with starting okay why
didn't the Guard unit start with
stopping and he did not start with
starting because you have to start
before you have to stop
so isn't a gardener illogical okay he
should have said there's no starting
there's no stopping blah blah blah but
he said first thing he said there's no
stopping and there's no starting later
he says the same thing with coming and
going right I mean a person should go
and then come back right
but he said coming and going then why
why he mixed them up is he just like
sleepy and I checked the sensor in the
sense but also says he starts with
stopping and then it goes to starting
and Tony Lamas says when you're dealing
with the impossible husband's anything
can happen okay when you're dealing with
impossible husband's anything can happen
if a husband is not coming from you he
can stop before he started so the
gardener wants you to say well what
what's wrong in the gardener why he
start with stopping he wants you to ask
a question the intelligence students in
this class I'm sure we're asking this
question why he starts and stopping why
he doesn't start with starting and Tony
Lamas has an answer okay Tony Lamas
enter if that thing is not coming from
you anything Gavin you know Katie's baby
can have Katie okay okay everything's
possible okay
in a world where the husband doesn't
come from you in a world I didn't do
anything husband anything happen husband
can have two heads
you know husband can be purple you know
everything can happen okay
how's husband yelling can come before
you open the kitchen door but that's
true always okay all right we're almost
finished with the homework I have one
more minute it's not gonna
yeah okay I'm just gonna I'm sorry to go
faster I know I hate it when my teacher
does done but here we go okay question
number nine what's the difference
between the emptiness of the person and
the emptiness of things okay all
emptiness is is divided into two kinds
emptiness of people and emptiness of
things okay all emptinesses are divided
into emptiness or husband and emptiness
of the pen okay you know normal stuff
normal things and then people all kinds
of emptiness are divided into two okay
in Buddhism okay now what's the
difference
the emptiness is exactly the same okay
the emptiness is exactly the same the
question is who has it who has the
emptiness in the first case it's a
living being fish dog human okay husband
why okay in the second case it's just a
thing okay like a pen okay you want to
go deeper you sure it's kind of late
yeah we better because it's on your
homework where do you put him
is it person or thing it's considered a
thing in the in the emptiness teachings
the parts of person count as a thing
okay there are thing when you say person
it should be someone you can call
Michael or Vivian or jasmine that's
person okay alright why we make this
division because the emptiness of people
has a special kind called the emptiness
of me
okay Michael Dawn's emptiness from
Michael Dunn is a special kind of
emptiness
okay the emptiness of yourself for you
okay Connie's emptiness for Connie
Kelsey is emptiness for Gelson JBC
emptiness for jb okay
what is your name whatever is your name
Luka okay whatever is your name the
emptiness of that is a special emptiness
for you why several reasons okay number
one it causes all the trouble in your
life it is the first link of the Wheel
of Life it is the blind man okay if
Michael doesn't understand Michael
Michael will compete to get things
Michael will hurt other people to get
things and then he will start the Wheel
of Life okay so a special kind of the
emptiness of people is the emptiness of
me me okay that's the most important
kind of emptiness if you don't
understand it you will hurt people okay
guess not
I like birthday cake I didn't get a
piece of birthday cake I'm thinking to
take it off
you know there's a little extra cakes
over there the spirits ate them already
right
then you still kick after then that's
misunderstanding yourself okay if you
want more cake then make sure you don't
get cake okay
if you want bigger birthday cakes at
Diamond Mountain which would be a nice
idea then share the cake with other
people okay
that's where they come from okay got it
so misunderstand me or mine or mine
this is my cake okay Michael's cake when
you say Michael for me that's a special
kind of misunderstanding people
misunderstanding me and my king okay all
right and that's the that causes the
Wheel of Life that causes - it's a
special kind of misunderstanding people
okay there's nothing yeah this is kind
of cool by the way this was one of my
guess a debate questions so I never
forget it because I almost lost but I
won when you see emptiness directly you
always see the emptiness of Michael okay
Jasmine when she sees emptiness directly
the first time she will see the
emptiness of jasmine okay got it
Chen Zhong will see the emptiness of
Chen Zhong Teddy will see the emptiness
of teddy okay so that's a very personal
emptiness okay the first time you see
emptiness directly it's always the
emptiness of whatever then fill in your
own name like those vows ceremony right
fill in your own name okay then later
you will see the emptiness of parent
directly okay but okay ready when you
are teaching emptiness you always start
with outside object that the audience
can see this is this is easier for
people to understand if you start
teaching although on its first day about
the emptiness of although he's never
gonna come back
so it's tradition teach the emptiness of
things first then go to the emptiness of
people but when you teach but when you
see emptiness directly it's always the
emptiness of you okay got it all right
we covered that question by the way the
misunderstanding of me and mine has a
special name in Buddhism okay it's not
called one kind of misunderstanding
people it's not called done it's called
the destruction view the destruction
view okay
it has a special nickname in Buddhist
philosophy it's called destruction
viewpoint okay why well first of all it
destroys your happiness okay if you
think you get more cake by fighting for
cake it will destroy your happiness okay
secondly it's destroyable
the viewpoint can be destroyed okay this
misunderstanding can be destroyed
thirdly it's often focused on me Michael
and Michael is destructible Michael will
die
okay Michael's getting older Michael
will die okay got it
so now you can call it the right name
which is destruction
viewpoint for three reasons maybe it's
on your homework
okay last question I'm just gonna read
the question then we'll stop okay so
have hope your bed is very close I mean
your meditation Christian number 10
iron the gardener is famous for giving
us new and cool proofs of emptiness
Choni lama describes forward different
ways in which these different proofs
work on us so when when someone gives
you a proof of emptiness like the two
husband demonstration right
how does it work on you what does it do
for you and Tony Lama says four things
okay he says four things happen he says
they're not the same and he says I'll
give you a homework assignment you
figure out why they're different and
then he never answers the question so
for this homework question just have fun
okay
just have fun I myself I don't
understand the answer very clearly okay
maybe you can figure it out okay so
here's a puzzle for all of us really
Tony Lamas says when someone gives you
the two husband's talk four things
happen four things happen they're
supposed to be different
okay every proof of emptiness has four
different effects are going on okay
I I don't understand them myself but
here they are okay number one it gets
you thinking about whether or not
something that you think you see can
stand up under correct logic okay can
can Allison stand up
under correct thinking correct thinking
okay yes or no cannot cannot so the verb
in Tibetan and send up like the idea of
Allison will crumble if you understand
about C's cannot stand up cannot stand
in that in the bright light of
intelligence Allison has to disappear in
the bright light of intelligence okay
that's the first one second one that
bright light of wisdom can destroy many
wrong ideas destroy ideas okay so maybe
in the first one the idea is that the
object cannot survive
Allison cannot survive in logic in the
light of logic okay but the second one
the belief in Allison can also not
survive okay that's part of your mind
it's not in the kitchen right when you
open the door alright third one those
proofs of emptiness should help you
learn to explore and not find anything
okay it's called explore and not find
anything it's like you're looking for
your hairbrush in your room but somebody
took it yesterday
okay I got it so you explore the room
where's my hairbrush and then you
discover you you never find it you
explore and never fun according to Tony
Lama this is a third thing that goes on
in your mind when you think about
emptiness if you think about and enos
correctly
guessing it's something like you go
looking for Alison she's gotta be in the
kitchen somewhere and then finally he's
saying you know you
the result is no reason you don't find
her okay now you guys have to decide I
don't really understand okay acquainted
Johnny llama it's important last one the
existence the very existence of certain
things it is denied in the light of
lunch their very existence of certain
things cannot survive the light of logic
now how that differs from number one
it's supposed to be different okay it's
supposed to be different okay
the existence of certain things is
denied by a certain state of mind okay
and according to Tony Romo these four
are important and they're different okay
and I don't I thought if you have an
extra hour to meditate today you can
chew on those four okay he does not help
us he doesn't answer his own question
but he says you should understand the
difference okay so good luck on that I'm
not gonna help you at all it's probably
hard to get that answer wrong if you
just write anything okay because there's
no answer
at least you should be able to list the
form but how they're different that's
another question okay let's do it man
down
Vivian are you ready
time anew
[Music]
sorry
you know
[Music]
[Applause]
okay cool thank you for not talking it
looks like you're doing very well and
thank you for working hard it's hard
work okay it's not like the old long rim
courses okay good luck